Guide to the Judy Juanita Papers, 1967-2016 RL.11542
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Judy Juanita papers
1967-2016
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Juanita, Judy
RL.11542
3 Linear Feet 4 boxes; 1 oversize folder
Judy Juanita (b. 1946) is a poet, author, and teacher based in the San Francisco Bay Area. This collection includes drafts and other materials from her debut novel, Virgin Soul, as well as correspondence and subject files from her research and activism in the Black Panther Party.
Biographical / Historical
Judy Juanita was born Judith Hart in Berkeley, California and grew up in nearby Oakland. Graduating from high school at 16, she enrolled in Oakland City College and took classes there for two years before transferring to San Francisco State University as a junior. While at Oakland, she joined the Black Student Union (BSU) and later became involved with the Black Panther Party for Self Defense (BPP) in San Francisco. Invited to edit the Panthers' newspaper, "The Black Panther," Juanita lived in one of the group's homes in Potrero Hill during 1967 while working on the Free Breakfast for Children Program. Graduating with a BA in psychology in 1969, she completed an MFA in creative writing in 1971 after teaching Black Psychology and Black Journalism at the first Black Studies program in the United States.
She became a published poet in 1980 and has published numerous poems since. Since the 1980s, Juanita has written and performed over 17 original plays. In 2013, her debut novel, Virgin Soul, was published by Viking Press. The following year, she published a volume of essays entitled, De Facto Feminism: Essays Straight Out Oakland." She is currently a writing instructor at Laney College (formerly Oakland City College) a school within the Peralta Community College District.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Judy Juanita Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2017.
Collection Overview
The first series, Biographical Materials, contains material related to Juanita's public appearances, coursework, transcripts, resume, and personal correspondence. The MFA coursework contains early writing that she did under the name "Judy Hart."
The second series, Writing, is primarily made up of content related to her novel, Virgin Soul, and includes notes, fragments, rough drafts, character sketches, reviews, and financial information. Further writings include novel drafts, play scripts, poetry, and short stories. In addition to handwritten and typewritten drafts, many works contain final, published drafts.
The third series, Subject Files, includes research materials related to Virgin Soul, including the history of West Oakland and of San Francisco State University during the 1960s. Also in this series are notes on writings, interviews with Juanita, press clippings, and posters.
Women authors, American; College teachers as authors; San Francisco Bay Area (Calif.) -- Intellectual life; John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture; Black Panther Party; San Francisco State University. Black Studies Department
- Personal Materials, 1967-2016; 1
  - Public Appearances, 1986-2015 (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Flyers and notes on public apperances
  - Correspondence, 1986-2014 (Box 1)
  - Work Diary, 1996-1998; 2 folders (Box 1)
    Notes on writing progress and ideas
  - SFSU Transcripts, undated (Box 1)
  - Peralta College, 2005 (Box 1)
    Application and hiring information
  - Resume, 1993 (Box 1)
  - MFA Coursework, 1967-1970 (Box 1)
    From BA and MFA coursework at San Francisco State University
  - Notes from MFA Course, 1992 (Box 1)
- Writings, 1980-2016; 2
  - Blue Jeans, Black Fist, 2011; 3 folders (Box 1)
    Full manuscript and correpsondence for "Blue Jeans, Black Fist" later to be renamed "Virgin Soul"
  - Junior for Real, undated; 2 folders (Box 1)
    Incomplete manuscript for what appears to be an early draft of "Virgin Soul"
  - The Hand, 2012 (Box 1)
    Published volume of the Crab Orchard Review with short story "The Hand" (page 70)
  - Virgin Soul paperback, 2013 (Box 1)
  - Virgin Soul synopsis and cover proofs, 2013; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Virgin Soul interviews and notes, undated; 5 folders (Box 2)
  - Virgin Soul character studies, undated; 6 folders (Box 2)
    Excerpts and character studies of Gee, Eddie (Woodie), and Allwood
  - Anatomy of a Virgin Soul, 2014 (Box 2)
    "Anatomy of a Virgin Soul" essays on writing of novel
  - Feedback and student papers, undated; 4 folders (Box 2)
    Feedback and student papers
  - Virgin Soul correspondence and financials, 1992-2016; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Between General MacArthur and Admiral Nimitz, 1998-2016; 2 folders (Box 3)
    Notes on short story "Hometown" which later became published story "Between General MacArthur and Admiral Nimitz"
  - De Facto Feminism, 2016; 2 folders (Box 3)
    Advanced review copy and notes, drafts
  - When did Cassius Clay Become Muhammad Ali, 2002 (Box 3)
    Spring 2002 edition of "Good News" a journal from Laney College
  - Not a Through Street, 2015; 2 folders (Box 3)
    Notes, draft, and published version of story
  - Poetry, undated (Box 3)
  - Aunt Jemima What Took You So Long, undated (Box 3)
  - Bling, 2012 (Box 3)
    Draft and published version of "Bling" in edited volume "Turning a Train of Though Upside Down"
  - We've Got Work to Do, 2007 (Box 3)
    Poetry Collection
  - Counter-Terrorism, 2003 (Box 3)
    A one woman play written and performed by Juanita
  - Literacy Through Drama, Poetry and Prose, 2015 (Box 3)
    Teaching packet
  - The Streetwalker, 1980 (Box 3)
    Poem published in "Bergen Poets" journal
  - Literacy and Homage to the Black Arts Movement, 2016 (Box 3)
  - The Gun as the Ultimate Performance Poem, 2014 (Box 4)
    Pamphlet and printed versions
  - A Place Called California, 2009 (Box 4)
    In Spring 2009 issue of "Good News", Laney College literary journal
  - Violence The First Time, 2007 (Box 4)
    In Summer 2007 issue of "Speak No Evil"
  - Making Room and Hometown, 2010 (Box 4)
    Self-published packet with "Hometown" and "Making Room"
  - Theodicy, 2006 (Box 4)
    Script for play and research material on slavery
- Subject Files, 1965-2010; 3
  - The Crusader, 1965 (Box 4)
    Photocopies of "The Crusader"
  - College in Crisis, 1970 (Box 4)
    Photocopies of book related to student uprisings at San Fancisco State University
  - An End to Silence, 1971 (Box 4)
    Photocopy of book sections on, includes notes and annotations
  - Research on Black Panthers, 1992 (Box 4)
    Handwritten notes from research at Merritt College Library
  - Interview with Judy Juanita, 2002 (Box 4)
    From Laney Tower newspaper
  - Bitter Grain: Huey Newton and the Black Panther Party, 1991 (Box 4)
    Book by Michael Newton with notes and annotations
  - Huey Newton, undated (Box 4)
    Research on Huey Newton, including FBI reports and law enforcement documents
  - SFSU Research, undated (Box 4)
    Research material and writings on San Francisco State University
  - Notes on Writing, undated (Box 4)
    Photocopies of pieces related to writing
  - CVs, undated (Box 4)
    Curriculum Vitae of others
  - Miscellaneous Research material, undated (Box 4)
  - Posters, Interview, and short story, undated (Oversize-folder 1)
    Large covers from "Virgin Soul", poster from Berkeley Food Institute, and "On the Menu" short story from Juanita